John Witherspoon Collection, 1765-1903 (bulk 1767-1798): Finding Aid C0274
Manuscripts Division
John Witherspoon Collection
1765-1903
1767-1790
Manuscripts Division
Witherspoon, John, 1723-1794.
C0274
4 boxes
Consists of selected manuscripts, correspondence, and documents of John Witherspoon, who was sixth president of the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University) and a signer of the Declaration of Independence.
Biographical / Historical
Born at Gifford, Scotland, in 1723, and a descendant of John Knox, John Witherspoon became the leader of the conservative group of the Church of Scotland. Persuaded by Benjamin Rush and Richard Stockton, both trustees of the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University), to come to America, he became the sixth president of the College of New Jersey (1768 to 1794) as well as a member of the Continental Congress (1776-1782) and the only active clergyman or college president to sign the Declaration of Independence. Witherspoon also helped organize Nassau Presbyterian Church in Princeton, New Jersey.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of selected manuscripts, correspondence, and documents of Witherspoon, as well as material about him. Among the manuscripts are a Latin address (1783) to the trustees at Princeton, a Latin oration (1794), and fragments of a sermon (undated). There are receipts (1779) for four Scottish prisoners-of-war, for whom Witherspoon made himself accountable; over twenty letters (1767-1768) by Witherspoon to Benjamin Rush, who was then a medical student in Edinburgh, Scotland; and letters to John Bayard, Henry Lee, James Madison, Jonathan Sergeant, George Washington, and others. One letter (1787) to St. George Tucker discusses Witherspoon's theory of education and the establishment of a grammar school. A signed circular letter (1784) to the Presbytery of New Brunswick seeks funding support in order to deal with consequences of the American Revolution on the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University) campus. Also included are receipts and bills from the Treasurer's Office of the College of New Jersey, two deeds, and notes taken by Abel Johnson (Princeton Class of 1784) of Witherspoon's history lectures. There are also documents regarding a case filed by Witherspoon in a court in the City of New York, dated 4 June 1793, against Lewis Morris for money owed to Witherspoon.
Additional accessions include material of John Witherspoon as well as material of members of his family. Included are letters by Witherspoon--one to his son David, another addressed "To the Public" (1774), and a letter to Aaron Burr--and material related to the legal suit of Witherspoon vs. Lewis Morris. There are deeds for land signed by Witherspoon's second wife, Ann, to satisfy debts against his estate. Also among the additions are some correspondence of his daughter Marianne Witherspoon Woods and her children, John Witherspoon Woods, Francis W. Woods, James S. Woods, and Margaret J. Woods, a receipt of Witherspoon's son David, and correspondence of other members of his family.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Letters from Potter to Davis and Ewing are a gift og F.S. Acton. Letter to Van Dyke is a gift of Clement R. Hoopes. Notes on Witherspoon lectures are a gift of Thomas A. Gleason. Letters and Portrait of Witherspoon are a gift of Harold T. Shapiro. The remainder purchased in 1978-2010.
Appraisal
No appraisal information is available.
Existence and Location of Originals
One box of the collection consists entirely of photocopies of correspondence, documents, and other papers, the originals of which can be found in the collection, the Library of Congress, the Presbyterian Historical Society, and other locations.
Clergy -- New Jersey -- Princeton -- 18th century.; Princeton (N.J.) -- History -- 18th century -- Sources.; Correspondence -- New Jersey -- 18th century.; Deeds -- New Jersey -- Princeton -- 18th century.; Documents -- 18th century.; Family papers -- 18th century.; Receipts -- 18th century.; Princeton University; New Jerseyana; Religion; Rush, Benjamin, 1745-1813 -- Correspondence.; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. -- Clergy -- 18th century.; Princeton University -- Presidents -- 18th century.; College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.); College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.)
- Series 1: Originals, 1763-1794; 1 box
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of original papers of John Witherspoon, including writings, correspondence, documents, and papers about John Witherspoon.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into five subseries: Writings, Correspondence, Documents, Miscellaneous Materials, and Papers About John Witherspoon.
  - Subseries 1A: Writings, 1770-1794; 1 box
    Consists of original manuscripts for the writings of John Witherspoon, including an address to the trustees and a funeral oration for Meredith Clymer, as well as others.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Address to the Trustees, 1783 October 7; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Delivered at the College of New Jersey in Latin.
    - Funeral Oration for Meredith Clymer, 1794; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Petitions to New Jersey Assembly, 1779; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Philological Dissertation, 1770; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Sermon (fragment) on II Corinthians, chapter 7, verse 10, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 1B: Correspondence, 1766 April 4-1794; 1 box
    Consists of original manuscripts for the correspondence of John Witherspoon with John Bayard, James Madison, Benjamin Rush, and George Washington, as well as others.
    Arranged by whether letter is by or to John Witherspoon.
    - By John Witherspoon to, 1766 April 4-1794; 1 box
      - Bayard, John, 1775; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Carmichael, John, 1779; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Fitzsimmons, Thomas, 1788; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Hogg, Baillie Thomas, Mrs., 1766 April 4; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5A)
        ALS to Mrs. Hogg.
      - Iredell, James, 1787; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Lee, Charles, 1790; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Lee, Henry, Colonel, 1770; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Madison, James, 1790; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Presbytery of New Brunswick, 1784; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12A)
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1767; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1768; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Sergeant, Jonathan, 1774; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Shields, Thomas, 1794; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Tucker, St. George, 1787; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16A)
      - Van Dyke, Nicholas, 1786; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1786; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Washington, George, 1783; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Witherspoon, David, 1777; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified receiver, 1770; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Unidentified receiver, 1786 July 10; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21A)
        ALS to "Dear Sir" written to Witherspoon's printer in Philadelphia. Also included is a letter dated January 17, 1935 regarding the contents of Witherspoon's letter.
    - To John Witherspoon by, 1767-1793 February 22; 1 box
      - Hyslop, William, 1793 February 22; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21B)
        ALS by Hyslop to Witherspoon regarding the location and a survey of land in New Jersey.
      - Jay, John, 1784 April 6; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21C)
        ALS by John Jay sent ffrom Paris congratulating him on his safe arrival in America, and discussing the practice of raising money for universities in America.
      - Porteous, William, 1786 May 27; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21D)
        ALS by Porteous from Glasgow, Scotland, regarding a remmondation he received for Witherspoon's nephew, Mr. French, to the vacant Parrish of Carmunnock.
      - Randall, Thomas, 1767; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 1C: Documents, 1767-1794; 1 box
    Consists of original documents of John Witherspoon, including bills, deeds, receipts, and agreements.
    Arranged by genre of material.
    - Accounts: Treasurer's Office, College of New Jersey, 1767-1771; 1 box
      - Receipt to Jonathan Sergeant, 1767; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Receipts for bricks to Joseph Horner from Jonathan Sergeant, 1770-1771; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Agreement: College of New Jersey and First Presbyterian Church of New Jersey, 1783; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Acknowledgement: Receipt of 4 Scottish prisoners of war, 1779; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Smith, A. l.: Court Case, 1793 June 4; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26A)
      Autograph document of a case of John Witherspoon versus Lewis Morris regarding money owed to Witherspoon by Morris. The case was filed in a New York City Court by Witherspoon's attorney, A. L. Smith.
    - Smith, A. L.: Account, 1794 January 18; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26B)
      Autograph document signed by Smith to James Morris, regarding Smith's expenses for the court case of Witherspoon versus Lewis Morris.
    - Bills, 1769 May 16-1773; 1 box
      - Hill, John, 1769 May 16; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Receipt for payment by Trustees of the College of New Jersey to Hill for work done to the College President's house.
      - Scott, Richard, 1773; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Trustees' Dinner, 1772; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Deeds, 1770-1794; 1 box
      - Castle Howard, 1794; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Stockton, Robert, 1786; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Memorandum of Account: Sergeant, Jonathan, 1770; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Payment Order, 1770; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Receipts, 1770-1779; 1 box
      - Morris, Lewis, General, 1779; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Rock, James, 1770-1771; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Testimonial, for Jacob Ford (Class of 1792), 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Subseries 1D: Miscellaneous Materials, 1763; 1 box
    Consists of miscellaneous materials, including a memo, a collection checklist, and biographical information on John Witherspoon.
    Arranged alphabetically by genre.
    - Biography: Witherspoon, John (TMs, 5 pp.), undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Collection Checklist, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Memorandum: "Things to be done", 1763; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Subseries 1E: Papers About John Witherspoon, 1784; 1 box
    Consists of papers about John Witherspooon, including Johnson, Abel: notes on the History lectures of Witherspoon and Pardee, Mary: letter from "Tusculum" to "Dear Henry."
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Johnson, Abel: notes on the History lectures of Witherspoon, 1784; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Autograph manuscript signed, by Abel Johnson, Princeton Class of 1784, 48 pp.. The manuscript is undated, but probably from 1784.
    - Pardee, Mary: letter from "Tusculum" to "Dear Henry", undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series 2: Photocopies, 1732-1799; 1 box
  These have been copied from originals in various locations.
  The material has been organized into subseries that mirror those of the originals.
  - Subseries 2A: Writings, 1779-1784; 1 box
    Consists of photocopies of writings, including a Memorial for the College of New Jersey and a Thanksgiving Day Proclamation, as well as others.
    - "Instructions" in regard to boundaries of the United States, 1781; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Memorial for the College of New Jersey, 1784; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Petition: Council and Assembly for the State of New Jersey, 1779; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Thanksgiving Day Proclamation, 1781; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2B: Correspondence, 1732-1799; 1 box
    Consists of photocopies of correspondence with individuals such as Benjamin Franklin, ALexander Hamilton, Benjamin Rush, and George Washington, as well as others.
    - By John Witherspoon to, 1732-1799; 1 box
      - Franklin, Benjamin, 1777; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Fitzsimmons, Thomas, 1787; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Hamilton, Alexander, 1787; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Holland, Samuel, 1785; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Lee, Charles, 1790; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Lee, Henry, colonel, 1770; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - "The Rev. Mr. Nisbet", 1767; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - "The Rev. Mr. Nisbet", 1767; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12A)
      - Pickering, Timothy, 1799 August 21; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Copy of an autograph letter signed requesting "one bound copy of the laws of the U.S.".
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1767-1768; 2 folders (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Sergeant, Jonathan, 1774; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Simms, Charles, 1784; 1789; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Smith, Jonathan, 1770; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Steuart, William, 1792; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - VanDyke, Nicholas, 1786; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Washington, George, 1732-1799; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Wallace, Archibald, 1767; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Witherspoon, David, 1776-1777; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - unidentified, 1770; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - to John Witherspoon by, 1767-1788; 1 box
      - Franklin, Benjamin, 1781-1784; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Rush, Benjamin, 1767-1768; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Stockton, Richard, 1767; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Washington, George, 1783-1786; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Witherspoon, John, 1781; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 28A)
        Photostat copies of correspondence and documents used by V. Lansing Collins in his biography of Witherspoon. Includes copies of correspondence with Henry Laurens Benjamin Franklin, and James Lovell.
      - Witherspoon, John, 1767-1788; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 28B)
        Photostat copies of forty letters and documents by Witherspoon to various people including Benjamin Rush, Robert Livingston, and Charles Lee. From various locations.
  - Subseries 2C: Documents, 1770-1791; 1 box
    Consists of photocopies of documents, including deeds, bills, and accounts.
    Arranged alphabetically by genre of material.
    - Accounts of Jonathan Sergeant, 1770; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Bill of John Witherspoon, 1791; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 29A)
      Photostat copy of a bill for Witherspoon's son at the College of New Jersey.
    - Deeds, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 29B)
      Photostats of several deeds for Castle Howard.
    - Deed: Mershon Land, 1771; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Subseries 2D: Miscellaneous Material, 1779; 1 box
    Consists of photocopies of the following materials: a booklist on "Titles of volumes once belonging to President Witherspoon...", a collection checklist, and The Pennsylvania Evening Post.
    - Booklist: "Titles of volumes once belonging to President Witherspoon...", undated; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Collection Checklist, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 32)
      (This checklist is not up-to-date)
    - The Pennsylvania Evening Post, 1779; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Subseries 2E: Papers About John Witherspoon, 1783; 1 box
    Consists of photocopies a letter of recommendation from La Luzerne to Vergennes.
    Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
    - Letter of Recommendation: from La Luzerne to Vergennes, 1783; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series 3: Additional Material, 1774-1903; 2 boxes
  Additional accessions include material of John Witherspoon as well as material of members of his family.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by last name and chronologically within.
  - Morris, James, 1793; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Three documents of James Morris who was the attorney for Lewis Morris in the suit of Witherspoon vs. Morris.
  - Price, Eoline Witherspoon, Document "Ancestors of Miss Price", 1903 February 6; 1 box (Box 4)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    AM 13914
  - West, Stephen to Ezra Stiles and Samuel Hopkins, 1774 January 4; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 12)
    ALS concerning plans to send two unnamed black members of the First Congregational Church in Newport, Rhode Island (known to be the freedmen Bristol Yamma and John Quamine) to Princeton for private study with John Witherspoon.
    Samuel Hopkins was the driving force behind a project to resettle theologically trained black men in Africa with the goal to missionize the continent and, as a result, halt the further enslavement of Africans.
    While Quamine and Yamma did study with John Witherspoon, neither of them ultimately did missionary work in Africa. John Quamine fell in the Revolutionary War in 1779 while serving on a privateer trying to win prize money to buy his wife Dutchess's freedom. Hopkins left Newport during the British occupation, delaying his plans. In 1793, he was again planning to send Bristol Yamma overseas (to Sierra Leone), but the plan failed and Yamma died in North Carolina in 1794.
    An overview of religiously motivated resettlement schemes in Rhode Island in the late 18th century may be found in the following article: George E. Brooks, Jr. "The Providence African Society's Sierra Leone Emigration Scheme, 1794-1795: Prologue to the African Colonization Movement." The International Journal of African Historical Studies 7:2, (1974). 183-202).
  - Witherspoon, Ann, 1795 July 6-1798 January 1; 1 box
    - Deed [copy 1], 1795 July 6; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 5)
      DS: Deed for land seized to satisfy a claim of Samuel Tucker against the estate of John Witherspoon signed by sheriff John Hardenbergh.
    - Deed [copy 2], 1795 July 6; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Deed, 1796; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 11)
      DS: Deed of land in Princeton to Ann Witherspoon by the executors of the estate of Samuel Tucker, signed by Benjamin Smith and James B. Machett.
    - Release and Quit Claim to Mary Magdalen Claveau Lombard for Tusculum property, 1796 November 23; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Deed to Thomas P. Johnson, 1798 January 1; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 8)
      DS: Deed for a tract of land near Princeton "being part and parcel of a large tract of land known by the name of Managrove farm". The document refers to a sheriff's sale of Witherspoon's property, and is signed by Robert Stockton and his son-in-law Samuel Stanhope Smith.
  - Witherspoon, David, 1781 May 28; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 10)
    AD: Receipt to Matthew Irwin for 100 Spanish milled dollars on account of his father, John Witherspoon.
  - Woods, David W., 1840-1853; 1 box
    - Letters to James S. Woods, 1840-1844; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 1)
      2 ALsS to his brother James S. Woods, Cadet at West Point.
    - Letters to Family Members, 1840-1853; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 3)
      9 ALsS to his son James S. Woods, his sisters Frances M. Woods and Marianne Woods, and his daughter Margaret J. Woods.
  - Woods, John Witherspoon, 1774-1841; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous ALsS of J. W. Woods to family members and others, 2 ALsS of John Witherspoon, 1 ALS to Aaron Burr to John Witherspoon, and a certification of John W. Woods while he was a senior in the Princeton Class of 1837 to be a teacher, written by Princeton University president John Maclean.
  - Woods, Marianne Witherspoon, 1837-1843; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 4)
    2 ALsS to her son John Witherspoon Woods, 8 ALsS to her daugher Frances M. Woods, and 13 ALsS to her son James S. Woods, Cadet at West Point.